Melick is a church village in Limburg (Netherlands)
on the right bank of the Roer, south of the
city of Roermond.
Melick belongs to the municipality of Roerdalen.
Traces of Roman habitation have been found
at Melick.
Melick's Roman name was Mederiacum.
In a deed of donation from 943 the village
is referred to as Malialicol.
The Heirbaan ran through Melick from Xanten
to Heerlen.
In the southwest of the village is the Kerkberg
street with a church hill where the Saint
Andrew's Church used to be.
This is the core from which the village developed
in the Middle Ages.
Melick was Brabant until 1494, after which
it came into the possession of the Duchy of
Gulik along with the rest of the Land of Wassenberg.
Until 1794, when the French era arrived, Melick
remained Guliks.
In 1815 it passed to Prussia for a year and
on October 16, 1816 (Traktaat van Aken) to
the Netherlands, where it has been part of
the province of Limburg ever since.
In the 19th century the village grew into
ribbon development along the Dorpsstraat,
and after the Second World War it became more
and more a commuter village of Roermond and
residential areas arose to the north of the
ribbon development.
From 1915 to 1932, the village had a stop
on the Roermond - Vlodrop tram line.
The line ran west of the Roermond road.
The stop was where the Julianalaan now ends
and had three tracks.
The line then followed the road to Sint Odiliënberg.
Four trams ran daily in both directions and
a ride to Roermond Station took about twenty
minutes.[2]
Until 1991, Melick together with Herkenbosch
formed the municipality of Melick en Herkenbosch.
This then merged with Vlodrop to form Roerdalen.
Melick is located on the central terrace of
the Meuse, at a height of approximately 24
meters.
The Roer Valley is occupied by the Tonnederhof
estate to the north and west of Melick.
To the north of Melick lies the important
industrial estate Roerstreek and Oosttangent
and to the north of this lies the Melickerheide,
separated from the industrial estate by the
Iron Rhine.
The first church in Melick is built in the
13th century.
Demolition, rebuilding, conversion and expansion
took place in 1891.
On February 4, 1945, the Germans blow up the
church tower.
The spire comes straight down and stops on
the ruins.
The English shellfire, coming from the other
side of the Roer, has almost completely destroyed
the church.
One chapel of the ambulatory remains.
In 1949 the patronage hall is used as an emergency
church.
Out of use 1954, has subsequently become an
association building.
The current Sint Andreaskerk is a large pseudo-cross
basilica with a floor area of ​​1,330
square meters.
Built between 1952 and 1954, when Melick was
still expected to see significant population
growth due to the arrival of the Beatrix State
Mine, which was never put into use due to
the decline of the coal industry.
Today the church is much too big for the village
and parish (1,600 parishioners).
Only 60 to 90 believers come to mass every
week.
They can easily go to the day chapel and the
priest's choir.
Due to declining church attendance and financial
problems, churches are being closed, sold
or demolished all over the Netherlands.
But they really want to keep church in Melick.
As a defining image for the village, and because
the church can partly still be used for church
services, provided only one or more new uses
are found for the rest.
That is why they came up with the creative
idea of ​​selling half the church
and staying in the other half.
The main nave up to the choir (680 m2) is
sold, the two side wings and the choir (650
m2) remain for the parish.
An architect, who is also a parishioner, has
made a renovation plan with a kind of block
system.
Spaces with walls can be placed between the
colonnade.
Blocks can even be stacked on top of each
other, creating two floors that can be reached
by elevator.
But who wants to buy half a church?
"We hope for a social function.
For example, a health center, museum or library.
A lot is possible, except catering, because
that is not allowed according to the Zoning
Plan," says treasurer André van Os.
The sale of the entire church is also negotiable,
but preferably not.
After all, the parishioners want to be able
to continue to church in Melick.
With the sale of part of the church, the parish
aims to be able to pay for the renovation
and preferably also have some money left over.
(source: de Volkskrant, 14-7-2016)
'On the road with Marius and Livia in Melick'
(7.7 km) is a walk around the village with
fun, playful assignments for the whole family.
A quote from the description: "You are not
the first children to go for a walk here.
Also a long, long time ago children already
walked and played in the area.
Two thousand years ago Marius and Livia lived
here.
different.
At that time, the Romans were in charge here.
They built major roads all over Europe at
that time.
One of those roads also ran through our village.
Listen to what Marius and Livia have to tell
you and play the games that they used to play."
The start of the walk is next to the church
of Melick at the pole with the Markoef.
Follow the walking route on the drawing.
The walk follows the story of Marius and Livia.
During the walk, a game is played on the numbered
places and a code is cracked.
You can enter the code on the route description.
After walking the detour you can enter the
code on the JongNL site.
The colorful route description is available
free of charge at the JongNL office (Marijkelaan
11a), at Slagerij Beulen on Kerkplein, at
Cafeteria 't Heukske at Raodhoes, and you
can also view it under the link above and
print it if necessary.
This playful walk is published by JongNL Limburg,
the umbrella organization of 43 local youth
work organizations in the province.
The local chapters offer young people and
young people a pleasant and responsible experience
of their free time.
JongNL Limburg is the Expertise, Training
and Activities Center for youth work in Limburg.